Ellen Swallow Richards Papers, 1882-1910
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Ellen Henrietta Swallow Richards papers
1882 - 1910
Richards, Ellen H. (Ellen Henrietta), 1842-1911
MS 130
2 boxes (.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Chemist and professor. Richards taught analysis of water, sewage, and air, and devised the first water purity tests. Involved in home economics movement, Richards introduced ideas of nutritious lunches in schools and systematic domestic science instruction. Materials include photographs, correspondence, notes and writings.
Ellen Swallow was born 3 December 1842 in Dunstable, Massachusetts. She received a B.S. from Vassar College in 1870. She earned another B.S. from M.I.T. in 1873 and, in the same year, an M.A. from Vassar. She studied for a doctorate at M.I.T., but never received it, reportedly because "the heads of the department did not wish a woman to receive the first D.S. in chemistry." In 1875 she married M.I.T. chemistry professor, Robert H. Richards, and devoted the next ten years to advocating for scientific education for women. Richards was the first woman elected to the American Institute of Mining and Metallurgical Engineers and in 1882 she helped found the Association of Collegiate Alumnae (later the American Association of University Women). She was also a leader in the effort to improve physical education in colleges. She wrote three books: The Chemistry of Cooking and Cleaning (1882 and 1887), Food Materials and Their Adulteration (1885), and The Cost of Food, a Study in Dietaries (1901). In 1884, M.I.T. set up a chemical laboratory for the study of sanitation, the first of its kind, with William Nichols in charge and Ellen Richards as his assistant. During this time, Richards devised the first water purity tests and, beginning in 1887, she was put in charge of the laboratory; she ran it during the groundbreaking study of water pollution in Massachusetts that modernized sewage treatment ("The Great Sanitary Survey"), commissioned by the State Board of Health. After teaching gratis in the women's laboratory at M.I.T for eight years, when women were admitted to M.I.T. on an equal footing with men Richards was appointed to the faculty as instructor in sanitary chemistry. She also taught analysis of water, sewerage, and air in the department of sanitary engineering, established in 1890. From about 1890, she increasingly concentrated on what came to be known as the "home economics movement." Among her many accomplishments, she introduced the idea of nutritious lunches in schools; worked for public support for systematic domestic science instruction; and carried on important work for the Society to Encourage Studies at Home, founded in 1873 to "help women who needed guidance and encouragement in acquiring knowledge which they could not go to school to get." Ellen Swallow Richards died in Boston on 30 March 1911.
The Ellen Swallow Richards Papers date from 1882 to 1910 and consist of .75 linear ft. of material. They are primarily related to her work as an advocate of higher education for women and as an expert in water chemistry. The collection contains photographs; correspondence; notes and writings; and printed matter, including scientific writings and selected tests, diagrams, drawings, and reprints. Of particular interest are writings and photographs related to water testing and pollution of Jamaica Pond in Boston (1900-07). There are articles written for the Association of Collegiate Alumnae (ACA) on the education of women, as well as Richards' books on home economics. The papers also contain correspondence and printed material related to the founding of the ACA (1882) and to the Society to Encourage Studies at Home (1873). The papers of Robert Hallowell Richards are located in the Archives of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Researchers may also wish to contact the M.I.T. Archives for information about the records of the Department of Chemistry and the Department of Civil and Sanitary Engineering.
This collection is organized into three series:
I. Biographical Material
II. Correspondence
III. Writings
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
According to a letter written in 1960 by Margaret Storrs Grierson, Nina Browne, Grierson's predecessor as Smith College Archivist and a friend of Ellen Swallow Richards', persuaded Richards to place her papers in the Sophia Smith Collection; no other details are known.
Search Terms
Richards, Ellen H. (Ellen Henrietta), 1842-1911; American Association of University Women--History--Sources; Ecology--Massachusetts--Jamaica Pond; Home economics--Study and teaching--History--Sources; Nutrition--Study and teaching--United States--History--Sources; Massachusetts Institute Of Technology--Faculty--History--Sources; Sanitary chemistry--Study and teaching--History--Sources; Women chemists--United States--History--Sources; Women scientists--United States--History--Sources; Water--Purification--Massachusetts-History--Sources
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL 1911-74, .25 linear ft.
  This series is comprised of several articles and clippings about Ellen Swallow Richards and her pioneering work in home economics and in chemistry, particularly as applied to water purification.
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE 1899-1910, .25 linear ft.
  This series contains letters from U.S. citizens regarding Richards' work in the home economics field, as well as correspondence on various subjects from professional colleagues. A significant amount of correspondence pertains to the Association of Collegiate Alumnae.
- SERIES III. WRITINGS 1882-1907, .25 linear ft.
  The series is comprised of typescripts, notes, published articles, and books relating to Richards' advocacy of higher education for women, to her study of water pollution and purification, and to her work in developing the field of home economics.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL 1911-74
  - Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biography and tributes, 1911-74 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE 1899-1910
  - Association of Collegiate Alumnae
    - General, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Academic members, 1906-09 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Quarter Centennial meeting, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General
    - Balch, Emily G., undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Balliet, Thomas, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Barrus, Annie, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Benedict, Francis Gano, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Bevies, Isabel, 1907-08 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Breckinridge, Sophonisba, 1906-08 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Brown, Elmer Ellsworth, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Calkins, Mary Whiton, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Clarke, Elizabeth Lawrence, 1900-10 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Coes, Mary, 1898-1905 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Cone, Kate Morris, 1899-1902 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Cook, Caroline J., 1905-07 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Cushing, Florence, 1902-09 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Dabney, Charles William, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Decker, Sarah S. Platt, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Draper, Andrew Sloan, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Earle, Mabel, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Franklin, Effie Scott, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Gill, Laura, 1905-08 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Goodrich, Henrietta I., 1905 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Greene, Mary E. Lewis, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Harris, William R., 1901 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Hicks, Verna, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Hussey, Ethel Fountain, 1908-09 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Jackson, Edith Talbot, 1907-08 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Kingsbury, Susan M., 1908-09 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Kinne, Helen, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Knight, Edward, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Langworthy, Charles Ford, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - MacMurphy, Archibald E., 1908 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Maltby, Margaret E., 1908 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Moore, Eva Perry, 1905-06 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Noyes, Lucia Clapp, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Pearmain, Alice u., 1905 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Salmon, Lucy 1908 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Talbot, Marion, 1895 (?) (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Thomas, M. Carey, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Van Hise, Charles, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Welch, William H., 1907 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Wilder, Constance, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS 1882-1907
  - Education of women
    - Typescripts
      - "The Ideal College Course for Women!", 1898 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - "The Ideal Course for Women to go into Effect in 1910", 1898 (Box 1)
    - Notes, n.d (Box 1)
    - Photocopy: "Tendencies in Women's Professional Education", (about Ellen s. Richards) The Woman's Journal, 16 Nov 1907 (Box 1)
      [See also Oversize Material]
    - Articles, 1906-07, undated (Box 1, Folder 48-49)
  - Metropolitan Park commission: water analysis, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Water supply and water pollution
    - Oscillaria Prolifica
      - Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
      - Reprints of published articles, 1901-04 (Box 1, Folder 52)
      - Tests and photographs, 1901, undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Jamaica Pond: correspondence and notes, 1900-07 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - General: reprints of published articles, 1902-03 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - The Woman's Journal, 16 Nov 1907 (Map-case Flat file)